Carlos A. Toruño P.

Development Economist (MSc.)

Contact

29 years old

Lichtenbergstraße 1
Göttingen, 37075

□ +1 (212) 461 4847

carlos.toruno@gmail.com

in linkedin.com/carlostoruno

github.com/ctoruno

Education

Oct. 2019 - Oct. 2021

Development Economics (M.Sc.)

University of Göttingen Göttingen, Germany

Master's thesis: Political favoritism and social protection policies: Evidence from a cash transfer program in Colombia.

Feb, 2010 - Apr, 2014

Applied Economics (B.Sc.)

Central American University (UCA) Managua, Nicaragua

Bachelor's internship at the Nicaraguan Market Competition Authority.

Feb, 2005 - Dec, 2009

High School Diploma

La Salle High School Managua, Nicaragua

About me

I'm a young economist from Nicaragua with experience as a researcher in development topics. I describe myself as a very organized and pro-active person with high performance in team working, but also as a curious individual with a high level of critical thinking. These characteristics have allowed me to integrate, quickly and easily, into a new professional environment without for getting that we are in a continuous learning process. My main topics of interest are policy design and evaluation, poverty, inequality, democracy, rule of law and governance.

Work experience

Senior Data Analyst

Apr, 2022 -

World Justice Project (WJP) Washington, D.C.

As part of the data analytics unit I'm in charge of coding the different cleaning, management, analysis and visualizations routines required by the research team on the General Population Polls (GPP) and the Qualified Respondents Questionnaires (QRQ), which are applied each year by the organization to both, general population and specialized lawyers, in several countries around the world.

Consultant for political and institutional topics

Nov, 2021 - Mar, 2022

Programa Estado de la Nación (PEN) San José, Costa Rica

Contracted as a part of a short-term consultancy to support the research agenda in political and institutional topics for Nicaragua. I was in charge of the design and analysis related to the Nicaraguan Post-Electoral Survey 2021 and I supported the elaboration of other specific studies including a diagnosis of the socioeconomic context of the Nicaraguan youth and the 2022 edition of the state of democracy in Nicaragua.

Senior Economist

Jul, 2018 - Jul, 2019

Nicaraguan Foundation for Social and Economic Development (FUNIDES) *Managua, Nicaragua*

I was responsible of the institutional department. This position involved searching for research opportunities, design study protocols, coordinate with other researchers and prepare discussion meetings with development aid agencies and other NGOs' officers. Some of the research topics covered by the institutional department are democracy, governance, rule of law, politics and civic political culture.

Research Assistant

June, 2016 - Jul, 2018

Nicaraguan Foundation for Social and Economic Development (FUNIDES) *Managua, Nicaragua*

As a research assistant, my main responsibilities were to help with the research agenda on social topics like education, health, poverty and inequality. Some of the frequent tasks involved in this position were to clean and analyze administrative data as well as household surveys, prepare tables and plots for technical reports, assist in the design and programming of surveys, perform balance tests and other checks on survey samples, carry focal groups with experts and targeted individuals, and assist in the meetings with governmental and development aid agencies' officers.

Data manipulation and visualization

7 years

Regression analysis

7 years

Survey design and programming 4 years

Program evaluation and experimental designs

2 years

Quasi-experimental designs

2 years

Geospatial analysis

2 years

Web scrapping and Shiny Apps

1 year

Natural Language Processing

1 year

Software

R

Stata

LaTex

CSPro + ODK

Python

Languages

Spanish	Native
English	C2
Portuguese	B2
German	A2

Assistant professor

Central American University (UCA) Managua, Nicaragua

Assist the economics department of the Central American University in Managua by giving the lectures and tutorial sessions for the undergraduate courses of Regulation and Antitrust Economics and Social Quantitative Techniques. More specifically, I was in charge of presenting topics related with my experience as an economic analyst at the national antitrust authority (Procompetencia) and as a research analyst at FUNIDES.

Economic Analyst

Jul, 2013 - Jun, 2016

National Institute for the Promotion of Economic Competition(Procompetencia) *Managua, Nicaragua*

As part of the economics department of the national antitrust authority I supported the senior officers in cases of unfair competition, mergers and acquisitions. As part of my main responsibilities, I had to clean and analyze firm level data, prepare tables and plots, delimit relevant markets for cases of mergers and acquisitions and write the subsequent reports of the economic analysis.

Publications

Master thesis:

 Toruño C. (2021). "Political favoritism and social protection policies: Evidence from a cash transfer program in Colombia". Document submitted to Prof. Dr. Krisztina Kis-Katos at the chair of International Economic Policy of the University of Göttingen.

Document available on this link.

Working papers:

- Toruño C. & Granada, D. (2020). "Local democracy in Nicaragua: Study case in the municipalities of El Almendro and Kukrahill" (Original document in Spanish). FUNIDES: Managua, Nicaragua Document available on this link.
- Toruño C. & López Espinoza, Á. (2019). "Diagnosis of the demand for technical occupations in times of crisis" (Original document in Spanish). RENET: Managua, Nicaragua

Document available on this link.

- Toruño C. & Huelva, L. & Pacheco, C. (2018). "State of Democracy in Nicaragua 2019" (Original document in Spanish). FUNIDES: Managua, Nicaragua Document available on this link.
- Huelva, L. & Pacheco, C. & Toruño C. (2018). "Effects of maternity on the labor supply of women" (Original document in Spanish). FUNIDES: Managua, Nicaragua Document available on this link.
- Huelva, L. & Toruño, C. (2017). "Impact of public expenditure in the reduction of poverty and inequality". (Original document in Spanish). FUNIDES: Managua, Nicaragua

Document available on this link.

 Huelva, L. & Pacheco, C. & Toruño C. (2017). "Quality of Education in Nicaragua: Does the children enjoy of the same opportunities?". (Original document in Spanish). FUNIDES: Managua, Nicaragua Document available on this link.

Data Projects

• Colombia 2022: A Twitter Companion

Shiny app that contains information about the different presidential candidates related to the 2022 Colombian National Elections with base on the daily activity registered over Twitter. The app is divided in three sections: a speech analysis of what the candidates say on their tweets, a social monitoring hub that presents a frequency analysis of what the community express about the different candidates and a sentiment trends panel which summarizes the results of a sentiment analysis carried on what the people say about the candidates.

A preliminary version of the app is available here.